<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Alex Hagen</title>
    <description>Welcome to my portfolio. I am currently a Ph.D. seeking student at Purdue University in Nuclear Engineering.  This portfolio shows some designs, publications, and open source codes that I've created. Feel free to email me if you have any ideas, questions, or requests.
</description>
    <link>/</link>
    <atom:link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Tue, 30 Jan 2018 14:31:13 -0500</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 30 Jan 2018 14:31:13 -0500</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.4.3</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Quick Script: Google Calendar Events Editing from IFTTT</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;As many “nerds”, I’ve gotten really into the quantified self movement.
&lt;a href=&quot;http://ifttt.com&quot;&gt;If-this-then-that&lt;/a&gt; is a great resource for that, letting you
script interactions between different services (that don’t necessarily play
nicely on their own: e.g. Amazon and Google, or Apple and anything).
Unfortunately, I’m picky about my data, so I want to be able to change the
time structure or name of these events.  Particularly, I track my work hours
and my sleep, and the event timing for these was 15 minutes coming straight
from IFTTT.  So, below I’ve written a couple scripts that I can run every
week or so to clean everything up and have it display nicely.  I hope these
help somebody.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script src=&quot;https://gist.github.com/alexhagen/98362c36ae0bfa9838d5b546e4cdc02c.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 30 Jan 2018 07:02:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>/blog/projects/google-calendar-ifttt-scripts</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/blog/projects/google-calendar-ifttt-scripts</guid>
        
        
        <category>blog</category>
        
        <category>projects</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Quick Script: Rename Files with and Without Git</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Renaming files is pretty simple, usually.  He’s a quick little script for
renaming files with &lt;code&gt;git&lt;/code&gt; awareness.  Simply put in the wildcard you need in
line &lt;em&gt;1&lt;/em&gt;, and replace the strings you need replaced in lines &lt;em&gt;6&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;9&lt;/em&gt;. Note
that this will not print out the error message checking from &lt;code&gt;git&lt;/code&gt;, because
that would always show errors when non-git tracked files are present.  Also,
don’t run this with &lt;code&gt;sh&lt;/code&gt; (i.e., don’t put &lt;code&gt;#!/bin/sh&lt;/code&gt; anywhere near this
script). The easiest way to run it is to just &lt;code&gt;chmod&lt;/code&gt; it to executable, and
run it with &lt;code&gt;./move.bash&lt;/code&gt;.  I hope it helps!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script src=&quot;https://gist.github.com/alexhagen/6417284f5fff86e04eed49623e7747ab.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 15 Nov 2017 04:54:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>/blog/projects/rename-with-and-without-git</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/blog/projects/rename-with-and-without-git</guid>
        
        
        <category>blog</category>
        
        <category>projects</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>KiDB</title>
        <description>
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 31 Oct 2017 11:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>/code/kidb</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/code/kidb</guid>
        
        
        <category>code</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Innovations in Nuclear Technology R&amp;D Award</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;In early summer, I received word that I’d received a &lt;a href=&quot;http://nucleartechinnovations.org/winners2017.html&quot;&gt;2017 Innovation in Nuclear Technology R&amp;amp;D&lt;/a&gt; award for “Students Attending Universities with Less than $600 Million in 2015 Science and Engineering R&amp;amp;D Expenditures”.  While that’s a mouthful, it was really flattering to be chosen for the award - given by the U.S. Department of Energy’s Office of Nuclear Energy.  The award material is really similar to my &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/work/ans_2016_ymg_award&quot;&gt;ANS Young Member’s Group Award&lt;/a&gt;, titled &lt;strong&gt;Detection of Special Nuclear Material in Cargo using Continuous Neutron Interrogation and Tension Metastable Fluid Detectors&lt;/strong&gt;, so I’m not going to expound on it here. I’m grateful to the DoE and my coauthors (Dr. Rusi Taleyarkhan and Dr. Brian Archambault) for this award.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/ne_news_screencap_innov_nuke_tech_2017.png&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
      Recognition of my award from Purdue's School of Nuclear Engineering
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 18 Oct 2017 05:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>/blog/work/innovations_in_nuclear_technology_rd_award</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/blog/work/innovations_in_nuclear_technology_rd_award</guid>
        
        
        <category>blog</category>
        
        <category>work</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>ICONE 2017 Best Paper Award</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;In July, one of my coworkers and coauthors received an award from the ASME’s
International Conference on Nuclear Engineering for our work on detection of
Radon using our Tensioned Metastable Fluid Detectors.  The recognition is great
for us, and the application is also very exciting.  Below is a screencapture of
recognition from our College of Engineering.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/coe_news_screencap_icone_2017.png&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
      Recognition of our award from Purdue's College of Engineering
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 31 Jul 2017 11:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>/blog/work/ICONE_2017_best_paper_award</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/blog/work/ICONE_2017_best_paper_award</guid>
        
        
        <category>blog</category>
        
        <category>work</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>A Plan for Making Projects</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;One thing I’ve noticed about myself is that I feel better when I &lt;em&gt;make&lt;/em&gt; things.
Whether it’s building something small at home, designing and having something
at work fabricated, or even if it’s organizing and creating the branding for a
team I play on, or a group I’m involved with, I like the process of design and
creation.  In that vein, I’ve been passively interested in woodworking for
quite a while - in the watch-a-million-videos-on-youtube kind of way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, woodworking requires a lot of equipment to do correctly. And
doing it incorrectly seems like you just end up making a lot of garbage.  So,
to be budget friendly, I’ve decided on a long term scheme for how to develop a
fully featured shop.  This may all be moot, though, because my move in a couple
months may have me move to somewhere that has fully featured makerspaces that I
can just get a monthly subscription to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My plan basically revolves around carefully planning projects, and then
purchasing the equipment required for each project, in order of least to most
equipment.  Then, to replicate each project multiple times, and sell it on
Etsy.  I plan to sell as many on Etsy as is needed to pay for the equipment
that I bought for the project.  Hopefully they sell!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Right now I have a couple projects that I want to do:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A console/mount station for all-of-the-electronics including enough power to charge everything and a usb-to-wifi hub, even if I have to write the drivers myself.
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Tools required: I think just a plunge router.  Maybe a belt sander.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A step stool for our kitchen.
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Tools required: I think a table saw.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A dining room table for our kitchen.
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Tools required: Jointer, Planer, maybe a biscuit joiner.  And definitely a belt sander if I don’t have one from before.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A bed.
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;I think I’ll have everything from before.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A mounted projector box for our patio.
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;I think I’ll have everything from before.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So my current &lt;em&gt;modus operandi&lt;/em&gt; is to design everything in CAD before I make
these.  I usually use Solidworks, but I think for the whole legal aspect (and
the use-on-something-other-than-windows aspect) I should learn Fusion-360 for
my first project and use it from there.  I’ll update as I go along!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 08 Jul 2017 18:34:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>/personal/misc/woodworking</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/personal/misc/woodworking</guid>
        
        
        <category>personal</category>
        
        <category>misc</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Quick Script: Wordpress to Markdown</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Recently I had the occasion to convert a bunch of wordpress posts over to a
Jekyll blog, including a bunch of pictures that I sent out for third party
hosting.  I wrote a quick/simple script and I’m embedding it via
&lt;code&gt;github-gists&lt;/code&gt; below.  It downloads a page via http, then splits it into the
&lt;code&gt;content&lt;/code&gt; and then an array of pictures.  Note that you’d have to change this
if you had pictures interspersed throughout your post, instead of all at the
end.  I don’t intend this to be a catch-all or anything, but hopefully it’s
useful to someone. Requires &lt;code&gt;BeautifulSoup&lt;/code&gt; be installed and
&lt;code&gt;imgur-uploader&lt;/code&gt; be installed and working on the path.  It only
converts/posts once per hour to avoid &lt;code&gt;imgur&lt;/code&gt;’s upload limits.  I hope this
helps someone!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script src=&quot;https://gist.github.com/alexhagen/2ca6dcddfa7c3858ec78829b21770194.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 01 Jul 2017 08:05:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>/blog/projects/wordpress-to-markdown</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/blog/projects/wordpress-to-markdown</guid>
        
        
        <category>blog</category>
        
        <category>projects</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Life List</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;I intend this to be a living document for my own accountability and benefit.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;iceland&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;label for=&quot;iceland&quot;&gt;Travel to Iceland&lt;/label&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;volcano&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;label for=&quot;volcano&quot;&gt;Climb a volcano&lt;/label&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;porcupine&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;label for=&quot;porcupine&quot;&gt;Travel to the Porcupine Mountains&lt;/label&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;thor&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;label for=&quot;thor&quot;&gt;See Thor's Peak&lt;/label&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;mini&quot; checked=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;label for=&quot;mini&quot;&gt;Run a mini-marathon&lt;/label&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;marathon&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;label for=&quot;marathon&quot;&gt;Run a marathon&lt;/label&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;fiftyk&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;label for=&quot;fiftyk&quot;&gt;Run a 50k&lt;/label&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;furniture&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;label for=&quot;furniture&quot;&gt;Build a majority of our furniture&lt;/label&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;soccer&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;label for=&quot;soccer&quot;&gt;Play soccer until I'm 38&lt;/label&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;fourteener&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;label for=&quot;fourteener&quot;&gt;Climb a 14er&lt;/label&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;northernlights&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;label for=&quot;northernlights&quot;&gt;See the Northern Lights&lt;/label&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;states&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;label for=&quot;states&quot;&gt;Live somewhere outside of the United States&lt;/label&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;tubeamp&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;label for=&quot;tubeamp&quot;&gt;Build a tube amplifier&lt;/label&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 06 Jun 2017 11:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>/personal/misc/life_list</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/personal/misc/life_list</guid>
        
        
        <category>personal</category>
        
        <category>misc</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>MWE</title>
        <description>
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 07 May 2017 11:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>/code/mwe</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/code/mwe</guid>
        
        
        <category>code</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>JDC</title>
        <description>
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 02 Apr 2017 11:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>/code/jdc</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/code/jdc</guid>
        
        
        <category>code</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
